Guide to the Ben Alper Photographs, 2013-2014 RL.11076
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ben Alper photographs
2013-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Alper, Ben, 1983-
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11076
4.0 Linear Feet 4 flat boxes (309 color photographs)
Ben Alper is an artist based in North Carolina. His series, An Index of Walking, won the 2015 Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Documentarians Working in North Carolina. An Index of Walking is a yearlong photographic project that explores the enigmatic intersection of memory, place, geography, and perception. Taken along the same daily walk in his neighborhood, the photographs depict the commonplace objects and spaces that comprise what could be any typical suburban area. Alper writes that "My walks have been a vehicle for exploration, contemplation, and looking; they have provided a structure in which to engage with the place in which I currently live." Collection acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University).
Provenance
The Ben Alper Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Collection Overview
The Ben Alper Photographs contain his series, An Index of Walking, which won the 2015 Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Documentations Working in North Carolina. This series consists of 309 9x6” color photographs printed on 8 ½ x 11” sheets of Hahnemühle Final Art Pearl paper. Alper included the following abstract about this project:
"An Index of Walking is a yearlong photographic project that explores the enigmatic intersection of memory, place, geography, and perception. Taken along the same daily walk in my neighborhood, the photographs depict the commonplace objects and spaces that comprise what could be any typical suburban area. My walks have been a vehicle for exploration, contemplation, and looking; they have provided a structure in which to engage with the place in which I currently live. Georges Perec coined the term infra-ordinary to characterize the mundane features of everyday life – glass, concrete, utensils, our daily rhythms, the way we spend our time. He advocated for an anthropology of the banal, a method of sorts in which the habitual is scrutinized with intensity. Perec wrote, “We sleep through our lives in a dreamless sleep. But where is our life? Where is our body? Where is our space?”
Time spent with the everyday spaces, objects, and rhythms of daily life reveals a wealth of information, most of which hides in plain sight. What is gleaned is often fragmentary and discrete; however, even the most ostensibly ordinary landscape is imprinted with so much – time, history, growth, decay, politics, and wonder. Caught somewhere between art and life, private and social experience, and repetition and chance, this project exists in the lineage of Happenings. Everyday I take the same walk and restrict myself to photographing one object or space which captivates me. These constraints delineate my route and process, but within these strictures lie opportunities for spontaneity, drifting, and subversion. As Rebecca Solnit avows in her book Wanderlust: A History of Walking, “exploring the world is one of the best ways of exploring the mind, and walking travels both terrains.” It is this hybridized and indeterminate space, at once physical and mental, that interests me. This fascination derives from my own tenuous relationship to memory and place. Many of the homes, neighborhoods, and towns that I’ve lived in are unsettlingly absent from my consciousness. More often than not what remains is an abstracted still image, devoid of meaningful context. Sometimes, I realize that memories of disparate places have fused into one another, blurring the distinction between separate locations. A composite memory of place is born – temporally and spatially incongruous, but nevertheless united.
These compound memories, when not unified by place, find continuity in shared emotional states or physical attributes. Analogous experiences, whether joyful, upsetting, comforting, or tedious, bond to one another somewhat inexplicably. Psychological correspondences always seem to prevail over geographical ones. With An Index of Walking, I hope to speak about place as a series of discrete and fragmentary components, akin to a puzzle that is missing pieces. This is also how I archive and recall places in my mind – not as unified wholes, but as fractional and lacking continuity. It has become clear to me that this project is more than merely a durational exercise indexing a series of walks in my neighborhood; it is also a visual metaphor for my own idiosyncratic relationship to memory and place. In her wonderful essay “On Keeping A Notebook,” Joan Didion writes, “the point of my keeping a notebook has never been, nor is it now, to have an accurate factual record of what I have been doing or thinking. That would be a different impulse entirely, an instinct for reality which I sometimes envy but do not possess.” This sentiment resonates deeply with me as I think about my current relationship with photography. When I began An Index of Walking, I envisioned the project as one rooted in recording, mapping, and descriptive representation. In reality, what I’ve created is an illusory portrait of a place over time, as much fiction as it is fact. It extends beyond the evidentiary impulse simply to catalog my surroundings. Ultimately, the work represents my desire to fabricate a space that is singularly my own and to liberate the photograph from the confines of factual depiction. If memory perpetually betrays those who call upon it, then initiating this project from a place of invention and abstraction may be a way of subverting the anxiety of forgetting."
The Ben Alper Photographs were acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University).
Biographical / Historical
Ben Alper is an artist based in North Carolina. He received a BFA in photography from the Massachusetts College of Art & Design in Boston and an MFA in Studio Art from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Alper’s work has been shown widely, including exhibitions at the NADA Art Fair in Miami, the Luminary Center for the Arts in St. Louis, Le Dictateur Gallery in Milan, Italy, Higher Pictures and Meulensteen galleries in New York and at Johalla Projects and Schneider Gallery in Chicago. Additionally, his work has been published in The Collector’s Guide to New Art Photography Vol. 2, Conveyor Magazine, Dear, Dave Magazine, Album Magazin, Yet Magazine and the catalog for Young Curators, New Ideas IV. In 2014, Alper was awarded a Peter S. Reed Foundation Grant, which supported the production of his first artist book, Adrift. He is also the co-founder of A New Nothing, an online platform for long-term visual conversations between artists.
Arrangement
Collection's prints are arranged chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Documentary Photography -- North Carolina; Alper, Ben, 1983-; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- An Index of Walking
  - 6:26 pm, September 5, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:10 pm, September 6, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 5:31 pm, September 7, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 12:54 pm, September 8, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:24 pm, September 9, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 7:28 pm, September 10, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:19 pm, September 11, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 3:17 pm, September 12, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 8:01 pm, September 13, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:02 pm, September 14, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:49 pm, September 15, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 7:06 pm, September 16, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 7:11 pm, September 17, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 5:16 pm, September 18, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 1:05 pm, September 19, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 8:18 pm, September 23, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 10:31 pm, September 24, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:56 pm, September 25, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 10:23 pm, September 26, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 2:03 pm, September 27, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 5:58 pm, September 28, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:42 pm, September 29, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:03 pm, September 30, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:37 pm, October 1, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 12:19 pm, October 2, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 3:42 pm, October 3, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 7:02 pm, October 4, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 2:53 pm, October 5, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:32 pm, October 6, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:49 pm, October 7, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 9:19 pm, October 8, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:18 pm, October 9, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 9:16 pm, October 10, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 2:07 pm, October 11, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 7:06 pm, October 12, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:51 pm, October 13, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 10:33 pm, October 14, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:46 pm, October 15, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:39 pm, October 16, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 5:54 pm, October 17, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:27 pm, October 18, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 5:11 pm, October 19, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:21 pm, October 20, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 12:47 pm, October 21, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 9:21 pm, October 22, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 7:43 pm, October 24, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 1:37 pm, October 25, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:00 pm, October 26, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 7:46 pm, October 27, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 5:13 pm, October 28, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:42 pm, October 29, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 2:55 pm, October 30, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 1:46 pm, October 31, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 10:11 pm, November 1, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:11 pm, November 2, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 2:30 pm, November 3, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 5:47 pm, November 4, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:17 pm, November 5, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 12:07 pm, November 6, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 10:43 pm, November 7, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 10:29 pm, November 9, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:32 pm, November 10, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:03 pm, November 11, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 1:53 pm, November 12, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 10:14 pm, November 13, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 7:30 pm, November 14, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 1:51 pm, November 15, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 2:48 pm, November 16, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:36 pm, November 17, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 1:24 pm, November 18, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 10:17 pm, November 19, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:08 pm, November 20, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:08 pm, November 22, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:37 pm, November 23, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:30 pm, November 24, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 1:23 pm, November 25, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:23 pm, November 26, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:25 pm, November 27, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 6:52 pm, November 29, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 4:41 pm, November 30, 2013 (Box 1)
  - 11:15 pm, December 1, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 11:05 pm, December 2, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 10:56 pm, December 3, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 12:34 pm, December 4, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 12:27 pm, December 5, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 12:19 pm, December 6, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 5:05 pm, December 7, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 8:42 pm, December 8, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 8:42 pm, December 9, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 11:35 pm, December 10, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 5:33 pm, December 11, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 7:16 pm, December 12, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 5:38 pm, December 13, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 7:05 pm, December 14, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 8:00 pm, December 16, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 10:50 am, December 17, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 4:55 pm, December 18, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 1:38 pm, December 19, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 11:47 pm, December 20, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 5:21 pm, December 21, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 11:39 am, December 22, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 4:20 pm, December 24, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 5:48 pm, December 25, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 5:42 pm, December 26, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 10:00 pm, December 27, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 4:39 pm, December 28, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 4:33 pm, December 29, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 2:33 pm, December 30, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 12:46 pm, December 31, 2013 (Box 2)
  - 4:42 pm, January 5, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 6:34 pm, January 6, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 5:15 pm, January 7, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 8:24 pm, January 8, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 3:25 pm, January 9, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 2:28 pm, January 11, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 3:36 pm, January 12, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 9:48 pm, January 13, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 8:19 pm, January 14, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 3:43 pm, January 15, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 7:40 pm, January 16, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 3:00 pm, January 17, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 10:09 pm, January 18, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 3:18 pm, January 19, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 12:12 pm, January 20, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 9:34 pm, January 21, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 1:58 pm, January 22, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 3:37 pm, January 23, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 9:57 pm, January 24, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 10:40 pm, January 25, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 1:43 pm, January 26, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 12:37 pm, January 27, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 4:12 pm, January 28, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 1:59 pm, January 29, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 2:47 pm, January 30, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 2:11 pm, January 31, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 6:11 pm, February 1, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 4:02 pm, February 2, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 10:55 am, February 3, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 7:35 pm, February 4, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 3:18 pm, February 5, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 1:50 pm, February 6, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 5:19 pm, February 7, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 10:49 pm, February 8, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 10:47 pm, February 9, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 11:25 pm, February 11, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 11:25 am, February 12, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 6:19 pm, February 13, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 11:38 am, February 14, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 9:57 pm, February 15, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 5:17 pm, February 16, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 10:04 pm, February 17, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 2:14 pm, February 18, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 1:51 pm, February 20, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 9:38 pm, February 22, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 4:14 pm, February 23, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 4:12 pm, February 24, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 1:43 pm, February 25, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 9:55 am, February 26, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 8:28 pm, February 27, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 7:00 pm, February 28, 2014 (Box 2)
  - 6:51 pm, March 1, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:06 pm, March 2, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 2:17 pm, March 4, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 1:29 pm, March 5, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:04 pm, March 6, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 8:48 pm, March 7, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 4:17 pm, March 8, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 4:10 pm, March 13, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 4:03 pm, March 14, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 4:12 pm, March 15, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 3:32 pm, March 16, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 2:55 pm, March 17, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 3:04 pm, March 18, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 10:16 pm, March 19, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 10:37 pm, March 20, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 9:30 pm, March 21, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 4:06 pm, March 22, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:11 pm, March 23, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 1:53 pm, March 24, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 2:53 pm, March 25, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 10:30 pm, March 26, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:20 pm, March 31, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:18 pm, April 1, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:32 pm, April 2, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 7:35 pm, April 3, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 12:23 pm, April 4, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 12:26 pm, April 5, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 7:31 pm, April 6, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:39 pm, April 8, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:50 pm, April 9, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 9:58 pm, April 10, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 2:01 pm, April 11, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:49 pm, April 12, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 7:15 pm, April 13, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 1:57 pm, April 14, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 10:00 pm, April 16, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 2:04 pm, April 17, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:10 pm, April 18, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 5:26 pm, April 19, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 2:11 pm, April 20, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 2:03 pm, April 22, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 2:18 pm, April 23, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 7:22 am, April 24, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 9:23 am, April 25, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 7:14 pm, April 26, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 10:47 pm, April 27, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 4:45 pm, April 28, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 4:26 pm, April 29, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 5:47 pm, April 30, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 10:14 pm, May 1, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 11:01 pm, May 2, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 10:11 pm, May 3, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 7:26 pm, May 4, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 7:30 pm, May 5, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 10:10 pm, May 7, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 5:35 pm, May 8, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 4:22 pm, May 9, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 5:29 pm, May 10, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 2:37 pm, May 11, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 7:04 pm, May 17, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 5:38 pm, May 18, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 5:11 pm, May 19, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 8:49 pm, May 20, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 9:51 pm, May 21, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 7:59 pm, May 22, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 8:23 pm, May 23, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 9:11 pm, May 24, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 10:16 pm, May 25, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 9:07 pm, May 26, 2014 (Box 3)
  - 6:06 pm, June 14, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:12 pm, June 15, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 5:52 pm, June 16, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 2:22 pm, June 17, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 2:09 pm, June 18, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 4:15 pm, June 19, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 2:11 pm, June 20, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 4:23 pm, June 21, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:32 pm, June 22, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:31 pm, June 23, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:39 pm, June 24, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:36 pm, June 25, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:43 pm, June 26, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:33 pm, June 27, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:44 pm, June 28, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:26 pm, June 29, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:02 pm, June 30, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 10:12 pm, July 1, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:42 pm, July 2, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:09 pm, July 3, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:07 am, July 4, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 6:15 pm, July 6, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 11:37 pm, July 7, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:04 pm, July 8, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:46 pm, July 9, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:01 pm, July 10, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:54 pm, July 11, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 10:56 am, July 12, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:21 pm, July 13, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:53 pm, July 14, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:31 am, July 15, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 6:38 pm, July 16, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:42 pm, July 17, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 11:24 pm, July 18, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:54 am, July 19, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:10 pm, July 20, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:58 pm, July 21, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 10:55 pm, July 22, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:57 pm, July 23, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:23 pm, July 24, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:19 pm, July 25, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:50 pm, July 26, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 10:00 pm, July 27, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 5:57 pm, July 28, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:12 pm, July 29, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:31 pm, July 30, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:39 pm, July 31, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:19 pm, August 1, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 11:48 pm, August 2, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:18 pm, August 3, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:27 pm, August 4, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 10:24 pm, August 5, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:17 pm, August 6, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:27 pm, August 7, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:09 am, August 8, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 10:29 am, August 10, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 10:42 am, August 11, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 2:40 pm, August 12, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:39 pm, August 13, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:39 pm, August 14, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 2:31 pm, August 15, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 2:39 pm, August 16, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 3:42 pm, August 17, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 2:20 pm, August 18, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:49 pm, August 19, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:38 pm, August 20, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:01 pm, August 21, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:38 pm, August 22, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 10:47 pm, August 23, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:54 pm, August 24, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 3:49 pm, August 25, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:58 pm, August 26, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:54 pm, August 27, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:45 pm, August 28, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:26 am, August 29, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 9:26 am, August 30, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 7:53 pm, September 1, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 5:13 pm, September 2, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 5:17 pm, September 3, 2014 (Box 4)
  - 8:55 pm, September 4, 2014 (Box 4)